Okay, so this video is going to feel a
little weird and definitely just jammed
straight into the middle of the course
and that's because I was driving home
from work and I was like, "Oh no, I
forgot to teach them how to do optional
parameters." So this is the video on
that. So um you may remember there is a
function called prompt and you can give
it a prompt say what is your name?
And then if we save this and we go over
to our running code, we get a prompt
that says what is your name? Leave that
stuff in here and we can come back. But
you may also remember that you can put a
comma and oh sorry you can put a comma
and you can put in a second string here
and this will be the default value. So
now if we go live
we've got an input and it has our prompt
here and it has our default value here.
So in other words, the way this prompt
worked um one it changed based on input
which we know how to do that with
parameters but two there was optional
input that you could give it. You could
give it optional extra parameters.
Well I am here to show you how to do
that. So here I have this function
called get random number and it takes in
a minimum number and a maximum number
and then it does math necessary to
generate a random number between the
minimum and the maximum inclusive. So
you can put in 1 and 10 and it'll
generate a random number that could be
one and anywhere between 1 and 10. And
I've used math.f floor. So it will
always be an integer.
So I could say um alert get random
number. Uh I want it to be between 20
and 25.
And if I save that and I come over here
to my code, I get 22. If I reload, I get
21. Reload, get 25. Reload, get 22. and
it's consistently generating random
numbers between that range. Well, that's
really great, but wouldn't it be nice if
I could just call get random number by
saying alert get random number and just
putting in the top of the range because
maybe I just want a number between zero
and 10. And that's probably a pretty
frequent occurrence if you think about
how you would use this function. If
computers start counting at zero and
you're interacting with anything that's
computerenerated, chances are you want
to include zero in your range. So
chances are you want to start at zero
and you don't need to tell it both. It's
nice that it's flexible enough to take
both, but it'd be nice if you didn't
have to give it a minimum number. Well,
that is what optional parameters are
for. So if you come here to get random
number, you can set a default value.
There are some rules with this though.
Any optional parameters must appear
after the required parameters. So for
example, if we are requiring a maximum
number, then we need to change the order
of these parameters. So we'd need to
take a maximum number and then
optionally we'd need to take a minimum
number. And then to set it to have a
default value, we'll set it to zero.
Okay. So when I call this,
I'm going to show you both of these and
we're going to go use the debugger.
Okay. So we got 24 and 10, but let's
come over here to sources and let's put
a break point on line 16 and reload the
page. Okay, we're about to call get
random number and we're going to pass in
20 and 25. If we hit next, if we hover
over max, it is 20 and minimum is 25.
Lovely. I broke this function because I
called this one in the wrong order. Um,
but we'll hit next and it generates a
random number and alerts it and we get
24. Then um, we call get random number
with 10. We hit next. The max is 10. The
minimum is zero. Because we didn't give
it a minimum, it set it to zero. So we
hit next. It generates those numbers and
then it alerts nine which is in fact
between 0 and 10. Coming back over, if
you want to make something optional, you
put it at the end and you assign it a
default value, meaning if they don't
give you anything, that's the value you
want to assign. I'm going to fix this
function call real quick so that 25 is
the max and 20 is the minimum. And so
now 25 would go into max. Because we
gave it a minimum, it'll set it to 20 on
the next one. because we don't give it a
minimum, it sets it to zero. And that's
how optional parameters work. And it can
make your functions a lot more flexible.